Guide to the Charlotte Jirousek papers, 1954-2014.
Jirousek, Charlotte papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Charlotte Jirousek papers, 1954-2014.
23-19-4123
Jirousek, Charlotte Ann.
4.3 cubic feet.
Correspondence, publications, research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, course material, publications, and other records relating to Jirousek's career and her interest in the textiles and dress of Turkey.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jirousek earned a B.A. in sociology from Hamline University in 1960, an M.A. in applied design in 1982 and a PhD in design, housing and apparel in 1988, both at the University of Minnesota. She was an assistant professor and curator at the University of Alabama from 1988-1992 and from 1992-2014 was the associate professor of textiles and apparel and curator of the costume collection in the College of Human Ecology at Cornell.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, course material, publications, and other records relating to Jirousek's career and her interest in the textiles and dress of Turkey.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Jirousek, Charlotte Ann.; Cornell University -- Faculty; Cornell University; New York State College of Human Ecology. Department of Textiles and Apparel.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Department of Fiber Science and Apparel Design.; New York State College of Human Ecology. Department of Textiles and Apparel
Subjects:
Costume -- History.; Fashion and art -- History.; Clothing and dress -- Turkey.; Textile fabrics.; Clothing and dress; Costume; Fashion and art; Textile fabrics; Universities and colleges -- Faculty
Places:
Turkey
Form and Genre Terms:
History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Material
  - Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Peace Corp material - Turkey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Master's thesis - "Pattern, Form and Color in Weaving", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Pattern, Form and Color in Weaving" Plan B paper by Jirousek for M.A. degree - University of Minnesota, 1982 (Box 4)
  - PhD portfolio (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - PhD thesis from the University of Minnesota "Applied Design in a Cross Cultural Context: Designing for Handicrafts in Jamaican Development", 1988 (Box 1)
  - Review - University of Alabama - Promotion, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Promotion and tenure documents, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II. Publications and Research
  - Correspondence, 1995-2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Papers and poetry by Charlotte, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Paper - Vegetable dyeing, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "More Than Oriental Splendor: Western Dress and the Levant" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The End of the Silk Road: The Decline of Silk Production in Bursa in the 20th Century" (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Importing Handicrafts from Developing Countries" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Alabama's Handwoven Counterpanes: The Other Coverlet" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wedding dress manuscript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Dyes in Rugs from the Milas Area", 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Chagall and Surrealism" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Designing in a Cross Cultural Context: Handicrafts in Jamaica" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Indigenous Textile Craft Materials in Jamaica: Survivals of Early Dye and Straw Work Industries", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Quilts: A New Look at an Old Subject" - Hennepin County History, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Establishing Policies and Procedures for the Organization of a Historic Costume Collection in the University Setting", 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Superstars, Superheroes and the Male Body Image: The Visual Implications of Football Uniforms", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Market Effects on the Design and Construction of Carpets in the Milas Region of Southwestern Turkey, 1963-1993", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "More Than Oriental Splendor: European Ottoman Headgear, 1380-1580", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Dress as Social Policy: Change in Women's Dress in a Southwestern Turkish Village", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Review of Jirousek article (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "From Traditional to Mass Fashion System Dress Among Men in a Turkish Village", 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ottoman fashion draft, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Silk article, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Ottoman Influence in Balkan Dress" - Chapter two (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Turkish Dress - Chapters 6 and 8 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Illustrations (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Textile article images (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Encyclopedia entry, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Project summary - Poster session - AAFCS, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Peace Corps certificate and publication, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Exhibitions, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "The Art of the Needle" exhibit notes (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cooperatives survey paper (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Notes on Jamaica (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Jamaica notes and correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Income Generation for Rural Women" - Workshop in Jamaica sponsored by the American Home Economics Association, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "The Carpets of Comlekci: The Process of Carpet Weaving in a Turkish Village: Film Proposal (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Subject files and notes concerning various projects, classes taught, and publications, 1970-1999 (Box 2)
  - Art history papers, files on Turkey, personal calendars, and notebooks, 1970-1999 (Box 2)
  - Comments on Suhandan Ozay paper, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ITAA annual meeting - Abstract for poster session, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Articles and label copy on pile carpets, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Information about Debbie Durham's thesis, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Weavers Guild of Minnesota, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - International Conference on Oriental Carpets, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memos, handouts, patterns, publications, correspondence concerning color studies and weaving, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8-31)
  - Notebooks completed by Charlotte, 1960-2000s (Box 3)
  - Folder about Ecuador, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Folder about tour of Turkey, 1960-1979 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Series III. Cornell Files
  - Course syllabi, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - History of costume course - University of Alabama, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Lecture notes - TXA 635, 1990-1999 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - FSAD 3250, no date (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - History of Textile Design, no date (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - India field trips, 2010-2012 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Research scholars, 2000s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - FSAD department matters, 2003-2013 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Department of Textiles and Apparel external review, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Curriculum development, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Costume collection, 1970s-19990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Apparel design - curriculum, 1990s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Faculty meetings, 2000s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1992-2012 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Internships, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Course material, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 11-14)
  - Grant proposals, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 7th annual textile conference, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Islamic textiles abstract, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Jamaica manuscript, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Research in Turkey, including correspondence, 1989-2001 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - NEH grant, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - ARIT grant "Survivals of Traditional Textile Technologies in Turkey, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Sample papers written by Jirousek's students, 1990-2000s (Box 4)
- Series IV. Photographs, Slides, Videos
  - Slides of Charlotte's works, 1970-2000s (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Photograph of Missoula Christmas with Jirousek family, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs from Antep, 1996, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs from Azdavay used in culture book, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photographs from Azdavay/Black Sea in Bulgaria, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photographs and negatives of looms and weaving in Turkey, Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Photographs taken in Turkey, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6-9)
  - Photographs used for article on Turkey, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Slides from Turkey and Bulgaria of looms, weaving, silk research, fabric shops and people, 1985-2000 (Box 5)
  - Lecture given by Nurhan Atasoy at the Johnson Musseum on turkish tents, 2005-09-29; DVD-3361
    Introducation given by Jirousek
  - Video taken in Yesilyurt, Milas and Buldan for research purposes, 2012-12-31; DVD-3362
  - Video taken of weaving, Karagoz, Agastya for research purposes, 1990-1999; DVD-3363
  - Video taken of shops, looms, schools in Tire, Comlekci and Yesilyurt for research purposes, 1990-1999; DVD-3364
  - Detailed description of what is on DVD 3364, 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Video taken of weaving in Uzumlu and Gaziantep, Turkey for research purposes, 1990-1999; DVD-3365
  - Video taken of Rumel Hisari, Bursa, Gumbet, Bodrum and Comlekci, Turkey for research purposes, 1994-06; DVD-3366
  - Detailed description of what is on DVD 3366, 1994-06 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Video taken of rug washing and travel in Comlekci, Milas, 1990-1999; DVD-3367
  - Detailed description of what is on DVD 3367, 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Video of silk production, silk institute, fashion runway show and travel in Turkey, 1990-1999; DVD-3368
  - Detailed description of what is on DVD 3368, 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Video taken in Buldan, Rize, and Artvin for research puposes, 1990-1999; DVD-3369
  - Video of travel for research purposes, 2008; HD-59